<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A work for none but angels &amp; men that is to be able to look into and to know ourselves, or a book shewing what the soule is, subsisting and having its operations without the body ... : of the imagination or common sense, the phantasie, sensative memory, passions, motion of life, the local motion, intellectual power of the soul ... Thomas Jenner has lineas composuit.</title>
            <author>Davies, John, Sir, 1569-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-01">2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37244</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D410</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27853</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10174979</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10174979</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44697</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A37244)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44697)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1381:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A work for none but angels &amp; men that is to be able to look into and to know ourselves, or a book shewing what the soule is, subsisting and having its operations without the body ... : of the imagination or common sense, the phantasie, sensative memory, passions, motion of life, the local motion, intellectual power of the soul ... Thomas Jenner has lineas composuit.</title>
                  <author>Davies, John, Sir, 1569-1626.</author>
                  <author>Jenner, Thomas, fl. 1631-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>39 p., [6] p. of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.S. for Thomas Jenner,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Prose version of Sir John Davies' poem Nosce te ipsum--LCCP.</note>
                  <note>Includes "What heaven is, vindicated from the vulgar mistakes and gross conceivings of many" (p. 29-39) which is attributed to Thomas Jenner by LCCP.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Soul.</term>
               <term>Salvation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="unk">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:44697:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:44697:1"/>
                  <p>A WORK For none but ANGELS &amp; MEN THAT IS, To be able to look into, and to know our ſelves. OR A BOOK Shewing what the SOULE Is, Subſiſting and having its operations without the Body; its more then a perfection or reflection of the Senſe, or Tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Humours; Not traduced from the Parents ſubſiſting by it ſelf without the Body: How ſhe exerciſes her powers in the Body the vegetative or quickning power of the Senſes.</p>
                  <p>Of the Imagination or Common ſenſe, the Phantaſie, Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſative Memory, Paſſions, Motion of Life, the Locall Motion, Intellectuall powers of the ſoul.</p>
                  <p>Of the Wit, Underſtanding, Reaſon, Opinion, Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Power of Will, and the Relations betwixt Wit and Will.</p>
                  <p>Of the Intellectuall memory, which is the Souls ſtore-houſe, wherein all that is laid up therein, remaineth there even after death and cannot be loſt; that the Soule is Immortall, and cannot dye, cannot be deſtroyed, her cauſe ceaſe<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h not, violence nor time cannot deſtroy her; and all Objections anſwered to the contrary.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thomas Jenner</hi> has lineas compoſuit.</p>
                  <q>In faelix qui pauca ſapit ſpernitque doc<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ri</q>
                  <q>
                     <p>Such knowledge is too wonderfull for me, it is high, I cannot attaine unto it,</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.6.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON</hi>: Printed by <hi>M. S.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Jenner,</hi> at the South-Entrance of the Royall EXCHANGE. 1658.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb facs="tcp:44697:2"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44697:2"/>
                  <head>Of the Soule of Man, and the Immortality thereof.</head>
                  <p>Why, ſince the deſire to know, did corrupt the roote of all mankind, did my parents ſend me to Schoole that my minde might be inriched therewith? for when our firſt parents cleere and ſharpe reaſons eye, could have approached the eternall light, as the Intellectuall Angells, even then the Spirit of lies ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſts, that becauſe they ſaw no Ill, therefore they were blind and breathed into them a curious wiſh, which did corrupt their will: for that ill they ſtraight deſired to know, which ill was nothing but a defect of good, which the Devill could not ſhew while man ſtood in his perfection; ſo that they were firſt to doe the Ill, before they could attaine the knowledge of it; as men by taſting poyſon know the power of it, by deſtroying themſelves. Thus man did ill to know good, and blinded reaſons eye to give light to paſſions eye, and then he ſaw thoſe wretched ſhapes of miſery, and woe, naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſhame, and poverty by experience; Reaſon grew darke and could not diſcern the fair formes of God and truth, and mans ſoul which at firſt was fair, ſpotleſſe, and good ſees her ſelfe ſpotted, hanted with ſpirits impatient to ſee her own faults; therefore turnes her ſelfe outward, and ſees the face of thoſe things pleaſing and agreable unto her ſences, ſo that ſhe can never meet with her ſelfe. The lights of Heaven, which are the fair eyes of the World, they looke down upon the World to view it, and as they run and wander in the Skies, they ſurvey all things that are on the Center, yet the lights mine eyes, which ſee all objects farre and nigh, look not into this little world of mine, nor ſee my face in which they are fixed ſince nature fails us in no needfull thing, why doe I want means to ſee my inward ſelfe, which ſight might bring me to the knowledge of my ſelfe, which is the firſt degree to true wiſdome, that power which gave me ability to ſee externals, infuſed an in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward light, to ſee my ſelf by means of which I might have a perfect knowledge of my own form. But as the eye can ſee nothing without the light of the Sun, neither can the mind ſee her ſelf without Divine light, for how can art make that cleere which is dim by nature, and the greateſt wits are Ignorant both where ſhe is, and what ſhe is, one thinkes her to be Air, and another fire, and another Blood, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed about the heart, and that ſhe is compounded of the Elements, Muſitians ſay our ſoules are Harmonies; Phyſitians, the complex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:44697:3"/>Epicures makes them ſwarmes of Atomes, which by chance fly into our Bodies, ſome again that one ſoule fills every man, as the Sun gives light to every ſtar, others that the name of ſoule is a vain thing, and that it is a well mixt body: and as they differ about her ſubſtance, ſo, alſo where her ſeate is, ſome lift her up into the Brain, others thruſt her down into the ſtomack, ſome place her in the heart, and others in the liver. Some ſay that ſhe is all in all, and all in every part, and that ſhe is not contained, but containes all, and thus the learned Clerkes play at hazzard, and let them ſay, it is what they will; there be ſome that will maintain it, the only wiſe God to puniſh the pride of mens wits, hath therefore wrought this confuſion, but he that did make the Soule of nothing, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd it when fallen to nothing, that ſo we might be twice his<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> can define her ſubtle forme and knowes her nature and powers: To judge her ſelfe ſhe muſt tranſcend her ſelfe, for fetterd men cannot expreſſe their ſtrength, but now in theſe latter dayes, thoſe Divine Myſteries which were laid in darkneſs, are brought to light: and this Lampe of God which doth defuſe it ſelfe through all the Region of the braine, doth ſhew the immortall face of it.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <pb facs="tcp:44697:3"/>
                     <head>VNDERSTANDING.</head>
                     <l>I once was Aegle ey'ed full of all light.</l>
                     <l>Am owle eyd now as dim as darke as night,</l>
                     <l>As through a glaſſe or Cloud I all thinges vew.</l>
                     <l>Shall on day ſee them in there proper hue.</l>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <pb facs="tcp:44697:5"/>
                     <head>MEMORIE.</head>
                     <l>A com<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>on Jnne all com<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ers to reteyne.</l>
                     <l>A Siue where good run<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e out &amp; bad remayne.</l>
                     <l>A Burrow with a thouſand vermine hydes.</l>
                     <l>A Den where nothinge that is good abides</l>
                  </figure>
                  <p>This ſhe doth when from particular things ſhe abſtracts the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſall kinds; which are immateriall and bodileſſe, and can be lodged no where elſe but in the minde. And thus from divers acts and accidents which fall within her obſervation; ſhe abſtracts divine power and virtue; again, how can ſhe know ſeverall bodies if ſhe were a body; the eye cannot ſee all colours at once, nor the tongue reliſh all taſts at one time, but ſucceſſively: nor can we judge of Paſſion except we be free from all paſſions, nor can a Judg execute his office well if he be poſſeſt of either party, if laſtly this quick power were a body, were it as ſwifte as fire or winde, which blowes the on one way, &amp; makes the other a ſpier, her nimble body yet in time muſt move, &amp; not ſlide through all places at an inſtant, ſhe is nigh and far above, beneath, in poynt of time which thought cannot devide, ſhe is as ſoon ſent to <hi>China,</hi> as to <hi>Spain,</hi> and returnes as ſoon as ſent, ſhe as ſoon meaſures the heavens as an ell of Silke.</p>
                  <p>As then the ſoule hath a ſubſtance beſides the body in which ſhe is confinde; ſo hath ſhe not a body of her own, but is a ſpirit, and a minde immateriall.</p>
                  <p>Since the body and ſoul have ſuch diverſities, we may very
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44697:6"/>
well muſe how this match began: but that the Scripture tells us,<note place="margin">That the ſoul is created i<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mediately by God, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Zachariah</hi> 12.1. <hi>ſayth the Lord, which ſtretcheth forth the Heavens, and layeth the foundations of the Earth, and formeth the Spirit of man within him</hi>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he makes the body of Earth, and in it a beam of heavenly fire, now in the wombe before the birth,<note place="margin">Erroneus opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of the Creation of ſoules.</note> inſpires in all men their ſoules, and without a mother ſends dayly millions into the world which neither from eternity, nor at once in one time lay them up in the Sunne or Moone, nor in ſome ſecret cloyſter where they ſleepe till they be awaked, neither did he make at firſt a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain number, infuſing part in beaſts, and part in men, and being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to take further pain would make no more; ſo that the widdow ſoul ſhould be married to the next body that ſhould be born, and ſo by often changing mens ſouls ſhould paſs from beaſts to men, theſe are fond thoughts; ſince there are far more born then dye, then thouſand ſoules ſhould be abortive, or others deaths ſhould ſupply their ſoules; but as nature Gods handmaid doth create bodies in time diſtinct and in due order, ſo God gives ſoules the like ſucceſſive date, which himſelfe formes in new bodies, which himſelfe makes of no materiall thing, for unto Angels he hath given no power either to forme the ſhape, or bring the ſtuffe from Air or Fire, nor in this doth he uſe natures ſervice,<note place="margin">That the ſoul is not tradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from their parents.</note> for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſhe can bring bodyes from bodyes, yet ſhe could never tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſoules from ſoules, as light ſprings from light, and fire from fire as ſome learned fathers that were great lights of old did hold, for ſay they, how can we ſay that God made the ſoule, and yet not make him the Author of her ſinne, for in her lies the corruption, for <hi>Adams</hi> body did not ſin but his ſoule, and ſo brought the body to corruption, So we would fain make him the Author of the wine, if we knew whom to blame for her dreggs; none were yet ſo groſſe, as to contend for this, that ſoules may be traduced from bodyes, between whoſe natures there is no proportion, but many ſubtle wits have juſtified that ſoules may ſpiritually ſpring from ſoules, which if the nature of the ſoul be tryed would even in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture prove as groſſe, for all things that are made are either of naught, or of ſomething that is already made of naught, no Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ever formed ought, for that is proper for the Almighty; if then the ſoule make another ſoule, ſhe muſt take it of ſome former ſtuffe or matter, but there is no matter found in the ſoule:<note place="margin">Reaſons drawn from nature.</note> then if her heavenly forme doe not agree with any matter in the World,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:44697:7"/>
then muſt ſhe needs be created of nothing, and that is only proper to God alone; again, if ſoules doe beget ſoules, 'tis either by themſelves, or the bodies power, if by themſelves what hinders them but that they may engender ſoules every hour, if by the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, how can underſtanding and will joyne with the body in this act; only ſince when they doe their other works, they doe abſtract them themſelves from the body; moreover, if ſoules were begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of ſoules, they ſhould move and change into each other, but motion and changes brings at laſt corruption, and then how ſhould it be immortall? If laſtly ſoules did uſe generation, then they ſhould ſpread incorruptible ſeed; and then what becomes of that which they doe looſe, when the acts of generation doe not ſpeed? but if the ſoule could caſt ſpirituall ſeed yet ſhe would not, becauſe ſhe never dies; mortall things deſire to breed their like that ſo they might immortalize their kinde, therefore the Angels who are call'd the ſons of God neither marry nor are given in marriage, their ſpirits and ours are of one ſubſtance,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matthew</hi> 19.</note> and have one father the Lord of Heaven. Who would at firſt that in each other thing, earth, and water, living ſouls ſhould breed, but mans ſoul which he would make their king, ſhould immediately be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from himſelfe; and doubtleſs when he took the Woman from the ſide of the man, he alone inſpierd the ſoul, for tis not ſaid he did devide mans ſoul, but took fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bone; and laſtly, God being made man for mans ſake, and like him in all, ſave only in ſin, tooke his body from the wombe of the Virgin but all agree, God formed his ſoule within<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> him then is the ſoule from God, ſo ſay the <hi>Pagans</hi> which ſaw by natures light, her heavenly kinde, naming her kin to God, and Gods bright ray, a Citizen of Heaven, confind to the earth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Reaſon drawn from divinity.</note>This cloud may be further cleerd by heavenly light, for queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſſe God made her, and made her good, and ingrafted her in the body there to grow, which though it be corrupted fleſh and blood, yet can it not bring corruption to the ſoule; yet this ſoule at firſt made good by God, and not corrupted by the evill of the body, yet in the womb is accurſt and ſinfull ere ſhe can judge by wit or chuſe by will, yet God is not the Author of her ſinne, though of her being; and if we dare judge him in this, he can condemn us, and yet be cleere himſelfe, firſt God from eternity decreed, what hath been, is, or ſhall be done, and that every man
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44697:7"/>
in his turne ſhould run his race of life, and did purpoſe to make all ſoules that ever have been or ſhall be, and that they ſhould take there being in humane bodies, or not to be at all; was it then fit that ſuch a weake event, weakneſſe it ſelfe, the ſin and fall of man ſhould prevent his execution, and councells fixed, and decreed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the world began, and that one penall law broke by <hi>Adam,</hi> ſhould make God breake his own eternall law; and revoke the ſetled order of the world, and change all formes of things which he foreſaw; could <hi>Eves</hi> weake hand extended to the Tree, rent a ſunder that Adamantive chain, whoſe golden linkes of cauſes and effectes remain fixt to Gods own chare; O could we ſee how cauſe doth ſpring from cauſe, how they are mutually linckt and foulded, and that on diſagreeing ſtringe doth rather make then marr the harmony, and at once view how death is brought by ſin, and how a better life doth ariſe by death, how in one his juſtice is ſeen, and his mercy in the other, we would praiſe this his decree a wiſe and right: but we meaſure time by firſt and laſt, and ſee the ſight of things ſucceſſively, when the Lord ſees all at once and at an inſtant he ſees all things in himſelfe as in a glaſſe, for from him, and by him, and through him are all things. His ſight is not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corſive by degrees, but he ſeeing the whole, ſeeth every ſingle heart. He looks on <hi>Adam</hi> as a roote, or ſpring and on all his heires as Branches, and ſtreames; and ſees all men as one man, though they dwell in ſundry Nations and Cit<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es; and as root and branch makes but one Tree, and the ſpring and ſtreame make but one River, ſo that if one be corrupted the other is corrupted alſo; So when the Root and Fountaine of man kinde did draw corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Gods curſe by ſin, this was a charge that did binde all his off-ſpringe, and ſo they all grew corrupted: as when the hand ſins, the man offendes, for part from whole in this, the law doth not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: ſo <hi>Adams</hi> ſin extends to whole mankinde, for all natures are but part of his Therefore this ſin of kind was not perſonall, but reall and hereditary; the guile and puniſhment whereof muſt paſs by courſe of nature and law: for as that eaſie law was given to all, to Anceſtor, to heir firſt and laſt, ſo the tranſgreſſion was generall, in our law we ſee ſome foot ſteps of this which take her root from God and nature: Ten thouſand men make but one corporation, and theſe and their ſucceſſors are but one, and if they gain or looſe their liberties, they harme and profit not themſelves alone, but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:44697:8"/>
their Succeſſors: and ſo the Anceſtor and all his heirs, if they ſhould increaſe as the Sand, their advancements and forfitures are ſtill but one, his civill acts doe binde and harme them all.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <pb facs="tcp:44697:8"/>
                     <l>There are a Crew of fellowes J ſuppoſe,</l>
                     <l>That angle for their Victualls with their nose</l>
                     <l>As quick as Beagles in the ſmelling ſence</l>
                     <l>To ſmell a feaſt in Paules <hi>2</hi> miles from thence.</l>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <pb facs="tcp:44697:9"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Trueth</hi> and a <hi>Lye</hi> did each a Lodging lack,</l>
                     <l>And to a Gallants Eare their courſe did take:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Trueth</hi> was put by, (being but meanly clad)</l>
                     <l>And in the Eare, the <hi>Lye</hi> the Lodging had.</l>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <pb facs="tcp:44697:10"/>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Smelling.</note>Next ſhe uſeth the ſmell in the noſtrels, as into them at firſt God breathed life, ſo now he makes his power to dwell in them, to judge of all Aires whereby we live and breath, this ſence is Miſtreſs of an Art, to ſell ſweete perfumes to ſoft people, yet it imparts but little good, for they have the beſt ſmell that cannot away with any perfumes, yet good ſents doe awake the fancy, refine the wit, and purifie the Braine, and old devotions did uſe incenſe to make mens ſpirits, more apt for divine thoughts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Feeling.</note>Laſtly, the power of feeling which is lifes roote, which doth ſhed it ſelfe through every living part, and extends it ſelfe from head to foot by ſinewes; as a net covering all the body, or much like a ſpider which ſetteth in the midſt of her web, and if the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt thread of it be touched ſhe inſtantly feels it by the touch; we diſcern what's hard, ſmooth, rough, what's hot, and cold, and dry, and moyſt,<note place="margin">The Immagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation or common ſence.</note> theſe are the outward inſtruments of the ſoule, and the Guards by which every thing muſt paſſe into the Soule, or aproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth unto the minds intelligence, or touch wits looking-glaſſe; the Fantaſie, yet theſe Porters which admit all things themſelves, neither diſcern nor perceive them, one Common power which ſits in the forehead brings together all their proper formes; For all
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:44697:11"/>
thoſe Nerves which carry ſpirits of Senſe, and goe ſpreading them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelves to the outward Organ, are there united as their Center, and there they know by this power thoſe ſundry formes, the outward Organs preſent things doe receive, the inward ſence retayne the things that are abſent, for ſhe ſtraightwayes tranſmits what ſhe perceives unto the higher Region of the Brain.</p>
                  <p>Where ſits the Phantaſie which is the hand maid neer to the minde, and ſo beholds and diſcerneth them all,<note place="margin">The Phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</note> and things that are divers in their kinde compounds in one: weigheth them in her Ballance, and ſo ſome ſhe eſteemes good, and ſome ill, and ſome things neuterall, neither good nor bad, this buſie power is working night and day, when the outward ſences are at reſt, a thouſand light and phantaſticall dreames with their fluttering wings keeps her ſtill awake; yet all are not alwayes afore her,<note place="margin">The ſenſative memory.</note> ſhe ſucceſſively intends this and that, and what ſhe ceaſeth to ſee ſhe commits to the large volume of the memory; This Lidger Book lyes behinde in the Brain, like <hi>Janus</hi> eye, ſeated in the Poll, and is the ſtorehouſe of the minde, which much remembers and forgets more, here ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces apprehenſion ends as a ſtone caſt into the Pond of Water, one Circle makes another, till at laſt it toucheth the Banke.<note place="margin">The paſſions of ſence.</note> But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the apprehenſive power do pawſe, yet the motive virtue is lively, and cauſeth paſſions in the heart, as joy, griefe, fear, hope, love, and hate; and theſe paſſions bring forth divers actions in our lives, for all actions without the light of reaſon proceed from paſſion; but ſince the powers of ſence lodge in the Brain, how comes paſſions from the heart, it ariſeth from the mutuall love and kind intelligence betwixt the Brain and the Heart. From the kinde heat which raigns in the heart, from thence the ſpirits of life takes their beginning, theſe ſpirits of life aſcending to the brain cauſeth a ſenſableneſſe, and imediately judgeth whether it be good or ill, and ſends down to the heart where all affections dwell a good or ill report, and if it be good, it cauſeth love, and longing hope, and well aſſured joy; If it be ill, it anoyes the heart with vexing grief, and trembling, fear, and hatred. Now if theſe naturall affections were good, or if we had ſuch ſtrength of reaſon, and eſpecially grace for to rectifie natures paſſion we might be happy, and not ſo often miſcarry as we doe, for we were but blocks without them; beſides there ariſeth another motive power out of the heart,<note place="margin">Motion of life.</note> which are the vitall ſpirits, born in arteries, and cauſeth continuall moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:44697:12"/>
in all parts,<note place="margin">Locall moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> it makes the pulſes to beate, and lunges reſpier, and holdes the ſinewes like a Bridle, ſo that the body retires; or advanceth, turns or ſtops as ſhe ſtrains or ſlackens them, thus the ſoule tunes the bodyes inſtrument, with life and ſence fit inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, being ſent by the body, although the actions doe flow from the ſoules influence,<note place="margin">The Intellec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall powers of the ſoul.</note> ſometimes I will this, yet I have not a power to expreſſe the working of the wit and will, for though their roote be knit to the body, yet uſe not the body when they uſe their skill.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <pb facs="tcp:44697:12"/>
                     <head>WILL.</head>
                     <l>Free to all ill, till freed to none but ill</l>
                     <l>Now this I will anon the ſame I nill</l>
                     <l>Appetite ere while, ere while Reaſon may</l>
                     <l>Nere good but when Gods Spirit beares y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſway</l>
                  </figure>
                  <p>To theſe high powers there is a ſtore-houſe,<note place="margin">The Intellec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> where lyeth all Arts, and generall reaſons which remaine unto the ſoule even after death which cannot be waſhed away by any Loethean flood of forgetfulneſſe.</p>
                  <p>This is the ſoule and theſe be her virtues, which although they have their ſundry proper ends, and one exceed another, yet each one doe mutually depend on the other, our underſtanding is given us to know God, and he being known, our will is given us to love him, but he could not be known to us here below, but by his word and workes which we receive through the ſences, and as the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding reapes the fruit of ſence, ſo the quickning power feeds the ſences, and while they do thus diſpence their ſeverall powers, the beſt needeth the ſervice of the leaſt, even as the King ſerves the Magiſtrate, and the commons feed them both, the Magiſtrate pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the commons by the power they have from their Prince; The quickning power would be, and there it reſts, the ſences are not contented only to be, but would be well, but the ſoul deſires endleſſe felicity; theſe three powers doe make three ſorts of men, for one ſort of men deſire as plants only to fill themſelves, and ſome like beaſts think the world is only to take their pleaſure in it, and ſome men as Angels love to live in contemplation, therefore the <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> turned ſome men into flowers, others into beaſts, <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> to Angells, which ſtill travill, and ſtill reſt. Yet theſe three powers are not three ſoules, but one as one, and two or both contained in three, 3 being one number by it ſelfe alone; a ſhadow of the bleſſed Trinity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:44697:13"/>Theſe meditations may draw from us this acclamation, What is man that thou adorneſt him with ſo bright a minde,<note place="margin">An Acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> madeſt him over all thy creatures a King, and an Angels Peer? O what haſt thou inſpierd into this dying fleſh, what a heavenly life, power, and lively life, ſpreading virtue, and a ſparkling fire! In other workes of thine thou leaveſt thy print, but in man haſt written thine own Image; there cannot be a creature more divine, this exceeds mans thought, to conſider how highly God hath raiſed man, ſince God became man, the Angels are aſtoniſht when they view and admire this miſtery,<note place="margin">That the ſoul is immortall, and cannot dye.</note> neither hath he endowed man with theſe bleſſings for a day, neither do they depend on this life, for though the ſoule was made in time, yet lives for aye, and though it had a beginning, yet hath no end Her only end, is never ending bliſſe, and that conſiſteth in beholding the eternall face of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, who is the firſt of cauſes, and laſt of ends, and to doe this ſhe muſt needs be eternall, then how ſenceleſſe or dead a ſoul hath he that thinks his ſoul dieth with his body, or if he think not ſo, yet would fain have it ſo, that he might ſin with the more ſecurity; Although light and vicious perſons ſay our ſoules are but a ſmoake, or Aiery blaſt, which while we live playes within our noſtrills, and when he dies turns to winde, although they ſay ſo, yet they know not what to think, for ten thouſand doubts doe ariſe in their minds, and although they ſtrive againſt their conſciences, there are ſome ſparkes in their flintey breaſts, which cannot be extinct, which though fain they would, yet cannot be beaſts; but whoſo makes a merror of his minde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and with patience views himſelfe within, ſhall cleerly ſee the ſoules eternity, though all other beauties of the ſoule be defaced becauſe of his ſin.</p>
                  <p>For firſt,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reaſon</hi> 1. Drawn from the deſire of knowledge.</note> we find an appetite in every mans mind to learn and know the truth of every thing, this is connaturall and born with him, on which the eſſence of the ſoul depends, ſhe hath a native might with this deſire to finde out the truth of every thing, if ſhe had time the innumerable effects to ſort a<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ight, and to climbe by degrees from cauſe to cauſe; but ſithence our lives ſlide ſo faſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way through the winde, as the hungry Eagle, or as the ſhips which leaves no print of their paſſage, of which ſwifte little time we ſpend while ſome things we ſtrain through the ſences, that our ſhort race of life is ended ere we can attain the principles of skil, ſo that either God who hath made nothing in vain, in vain hath given this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:44697:14"/>
and Flower, or elſe our knowledge which is begun here, muſt be perfected in heaven. To one whole kind the Allmighty never gave a power, but moſt part of that kinde did uſe the ſame, as though ſome eyes be blind, yet moſt eyes can ſee perfectly, ſo though ſome be lame in their limbs, yet moſt can walke, but no ſoule can know the truth in this life ſo perfectly, as it hath power to doe; if then perfection is not to be found here below, he muſt aſcend higher where it is to be obtained. Again, how can ſhe but be immortall,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reaſon</hi> 2. Drawn from the Motion of the Soule.</note> when with the motion of her will and underſtanding ſhe ſtill aſpiers to eternity, and is never at reſt tell ſhe attaineth thereunto; water in conduit pipes can ariſe no higher then the well head, from which they ſpringe.</p>
                  <p>Therefore ſince ſhe doth aſpier to the Almighty ſhe muſt be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, the nature of all moveable things, are to move to things of their own kinde, as the earth downward, and the fire aſcends tell both touch their proper elements;<note place="margin">The Soul compared to a River.</note> and as the thirſty earth ſuckes her moyſture from the Sea to fill her empty veines, and ſo glides along her graſſie plaines, ſhe ſtayes long as loath to leave the land, out of whoſe ſides ſhe came, ſhe taſts all places, and turns on every hand, unwilling to forſake her flowery bankes, yet nature doth ſo carry and lead her ſtreames, that ſhe makes no finall ſtay tell ſhe return into the boſome of the Ocean. Even ſo the Spirit of God doth ſecretly infuſe into this earthy mould our ſoules, which at firſt doth behold this world, and at firſt her mothers earth ſhe holdeth dear, and embracerh the world and worldly things, ſhe flyes cloſe to the earth, and hovers here, and mounts not up with her celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all winges, and cannot light on any thing which doth agree with her heavenly nature, ſhe cannot reſt nor fix her thoughts, neither can ſhe be contented with any thing, for who ever found it in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, wealth, or pleaſure; and having his health, ceaſed to wiſh, or having wiſdome, was not vexed in minde, as a Bee that lights on every flower, and ſucks and taſteth on all, but being pleaſed with none at laſt ariſeth and ſores away, like <hi>Noahs</hi> dove flyes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Arke from whence ſhe came.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <pb facs="tcp:44697:14"/>
                     <l>When Hearing, Seeing, Tasting, Smelling's paſt:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Feeling</hi> (as long as life remaines) doth laſt</l>
                     <l>Mayde reach my Lute, J am not well indeede:</l>
                     <l>O pitty-mee, my Bird hath made mee bleede.</l>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <pb facs="tcp:44697:16"/>
                     <head>FANCIE.</head>
                     <l>Ape-like I all thinges imitate,</l>
                     <l>Dreame-like I them vary-ſtraite.</l>
                     <l>New proiects faſhions I inuent,</l>
                     <l>All Shapes to head &amp; harte preſent.</l>
                  </figure>
                  <p>Hence it is that Ideots, although they have a mind able to know the truth, and chuſe that which is good, if ſhe could find ſuch fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures in the Brain, as ſhe might find provided, ſhe were in her right temper, but if a frenſie doe poſſeſſe it, it ſo blots and diſturbes the formes of things, Phantaſie proves altogether vain, and brings no
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:44697:17"/>
true relation to the underſtanding, then the ſoule admits all for truth, and buildes falſe concluſions, flyes the good, and perſewes the Ill, beleeving all that this falſe ſpie propounds, but purge the humours, and appeaſe the rage which wrought this diſtemper in the Phantaſie, then will the wit which never had diſeaſe, diſcourſe as it ought, and judge diſcreetly, for the eye hath its perfect power of ſight, although the ſtreame be troubled, then theſe defects are in the ſences, and not in the ſoule, ſhe looſeth not her power to ſee, although her windowes be choked with miſts, and clouds, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections are not in the agent, but inſtrument, the ſoule hath one intelligence in all; in infants, and old men, although too much moyſture be in the brain of the one, and too much drineſſe in the other, which makes them that they cannot attain the outward printes of things, then the ſoul wanting work is idle, and we call the one childiſhneſſe, and the other dotage; yet the ſoule hath a quick and active wit, if ſhe had apt tooles to worke withall, and ſtuffe, for give her but Organs fit, and objects fair, give but the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged man the ſence of the younge man, and ſhe will ſtraight way ſhew then her wonted excellency, and as an old harper, although he hath all his Crochets in his Brain, yet can he not expreſſe it when the gout is in his fingers; then dotage is no weakneſſe of the minde, but of the ſenſe, for if that did waſt, we ſhould find it in all old men, but moſt of them even at their dying houre have a minde more quick and lively, and uſe their underſtanding power better then in their youth, and their dying ſpeeches are admired.</p>
                  <p>But it may be further objected, if all her Organs dye,<note place="margin">Objection.</note> then hath the ſoule no powers to uſe, and is extincte becauſe ſhe cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to act, and if her powers be dead, then what is ſhe, for ſome power ſpringes from every thing, and actings proceed from them, therefore kill her power, and act, and deſtroy her. Its very true, the death of the body is the deſtruction of the ſences, ſo that ſhe cannot uſe thoſe faculties, although their root ſtill reſt in her ſubſtance, but as the body when it lives by the wit and will, can judge and chuſe without the aid of the body, ſo when the body can ſerve her no longer, and her ſences are extinct, yet can ſhe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in heavenly contemplation all alone, of what ſhe hath heard and learned: and as a man that hath good horſemanſhip, and can play well on a lute, if thou take both horſe and lute away, yet he ſtill retains his skill, and can put that forth if they be returned unto
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:44697:18"/>
him, when the body revives they ſhall be able to fulfill all their wanted offices. But it may be further objected, How ſhall ſhe employ her ſelf, ſeeing all her ſences be gon? ſhe may keep and enjoy what ſhe hath got, but hath no means to underſtand or to get more, then what doe thoſe poor ſoules which get nothing, or thoſe that cannot keep what they have got, like lives which let all out, theſe ſoules muſt ſleepe for want of exerciſe.</p>
                  <p>See how man argues againſt himſelfe; Why ſhould we not have other means to know? as children in the wombe live by the navil, but being come forth are nouriſhed otherwiſe, children if they had uſe of their ſences, and could hear their mothers tell them, that in a ſhort time they ſhould come from thence, they then would fear their birth, more then we fear our death, and would cry out, that if their navill ſtrings were cut, how ſhould their lifes be preſerved? ſince no other conduit brings their food; and if a man ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply unto thoſe babes, and tell them when they come into this fair world, they ſhall ſee the Sun, Moon and Stars, Sea and earth, and meet with ten thouſand dainties, which they ſhall take in with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in their mouthes, which ſhall be cordiall as well as ſweet and their little limbs ſhall grow unto tall bodies they would thinke it a fable, as we doe of the Story of the Golden age, or as among us many ſenſuall ſpirits hold the world to come a feined ſtage, yet thoſe infants ſhall find it true. So when the ſoule is born, for death is nothing but the ſoules birth, ſhe ſhall ſee ten thouſand things beyond her imagination, and know them in an unknown manner, them ſhall ſhe ſee no more by ſpectacles, nor hear no more by her double Spies, her ſelfe in inſtant will all things explore, for every thing is preſent to her, and lyes before her.</p>
                  <p>But ſtill it may be objected, if the ſoules departed doe live, why do they not return to bring us newes of the ſtrange world wherein they ſee ſuch wonders, vain man we doe beleeve that men live under the Zenith of both the frozen poles, although none come from thence to tell us: So cannot we have the like faith of our ſoules, the ſoule hath no more to doe here, then we have to returne into our mothers womb, what man did ever covet it, although we all come from thence: and that ſhewes the ſoule hath a good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they never deſire to come hither again; doubtleſſe ſuch ſoules as mount up ſo high as to ſee their Creators face, holds this in ſo baſe an account, as that ſhe looks down and ſcorns this wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:44697:18"/>
place. As for ſuch as are detruded to hell, if they would come here, yet they cannot, but ſtill there are ſome wicked ones as ſay, that politick men have ſpread this lye of heaven and hell only to make men virtuous, ſo then it ſeems morall virtues be good, but they ſpeake this for their private gain, for that is the ſtanding of Common-wealths, wherein their private benefit is interreſted, but how can that be falſe that the Chriſtian, Jew, Turke, Perſian, Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Canibal hold to be true, this doctrine entred not into the ear, but is native in the breaſt, if death ſhould deſtroy man for whoſe ſake all things was made, then ſhould he be more miſerable then Dawes, Trees, and Rockes, which laſt longer then he who is taken away at an inſtant, but bleſſed be that great power that hath bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed man with longer life then heaven and earth, and hath infuſed into man mortall powers not ſubject to the grave, for although the ſoul ſeeme to bear about it her grave, and almoſt buried alive in this world, ſhe needs not to fear the death of the body, for when this ſhell is broke, there comes forth a chicken, for as there are three eſſentiall powers of the ſoule, the quickning power, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Sence, and alſo of reaſon, there be alſo three kinds of life defined her, in her due ſeaſon to perfect them all; The firſt life which is vegitive is that nurſing power ſpent in the wombe, where when ſhe finds defects of nouriſhment, ſhe expells her body and growes too bigge for that place, and comes into the world where all his ſences are in perfection, where he finds flowers to ſmell, and fruits to taſt, ſees ſundry formes, and hears varieties of ſounds, and when he hath paſt ſomtime upon this ſtage, his reaſon begins to be awaked, which although ſhe ſpringes when ſences begin to fade by reaſon of age; yet can ſhe make here no perfect practice.</p>
                  <p>Then doth the aſpiring ſoul leave the body, which we call death, but were it known to all what life our ſoules receive by this death, they would rather call it a birth, or Gaole delivery; for in this third life reaſon will be ſo bright, as her ſparkes will be like the Sun beames, and ſhall the reall <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ght enjoy of God, being ſtill increaſt by divine influence. Then let us take up this acclamation: O ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant poor man, what beareſt thou lockt up in the casket of thy breaſt, what Jewels and what riches, and what heavenly treaſure haſt thou in ſo weak a cheſt. Looke into thy ſoule and thou ſhalt ſee ſuch virtues, honour, and pleaſure, and whatſoever is counted excellent in this life. Thinke of her worth, and then know that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:44697:19"/>
God did mean thy worthy mind ſhould embrace worthy things; Blot not her beauties with unclean thoughts; neither diſhonour her with thy baſe paſſions; deſtroy not her quickning power with ſurfeitings and drunkenneſſe; let not her ſenſitive power be mar'd with ſenſualities and fleſhly deſires; &amp; let not her ſerious thoughts be employed on idle things, and enſlave not her will to vanity, and whenſoever thou thinkeſt of her eternity, have not this evill thought of her, that death is againſt her nature, no aſſure thy ſelfe it is a birth in which ſhe is brought forth to a better being, and when thou comeſt to dye, ſing and rejoyce as a ſwan, that thou art a going to bliſſe; if thou have faith to beleeve in Jeſus Chriſt that thy ſinns may be forgiven thee, and whereas before thou did'ſt fear as a child which is in the darke, fear not now having this light brought into thee: and now O thou my ſoule turn thine eye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and view the rayes and beams of thy divine forme, and know that whilſt thou art clouded with this fleſh of thine, thou canſt not know any thing perfectly; ſtudy the higheſt and beſt things, but retayne an humble thought of thy ſelfe, caſt down thy ſelf, and ſtrive to raiſe the glorious and ſacred name of thy Maker and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Redeemer; uſe all thy powers to praiſe that bleſſed power which gives thee power to be, and alſo power to uſe thoſe powers thou art endewed withall, and thus ſhut up all and ſay, <hi>O the depth of the riches both of the wiſdome and knowledge of God, how unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able are his Judgments, and his wayes paſt finding out,</hi> Of him and through him, and to him are all things, to whom be glory for ever.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="unk">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:44697:19"/>
                  <p>WHAT HEAVEN IS, VINDICATED From the Vulgar miſtakes, and groſſe conceivings of many; ſome of which miſtakes is mention made in this Title, the reſt of them manifeſted and enlarged in the enſuing Treatiſe.</p>
                  <p>AS
<list>
                        <item>I. Miſtake of Heaven is, that fancey the happineſſe of Heaven to conſiſt only in things without them, and look upon it only as an outward place, and not as an inward ſtate and diſpoſition of the Soule.</item>
                        <item>II. Groſſe conceit of Heaven is, as if it were nothing but a Theatre, a place of ſights and ſhowes, and God himſelfe were nothing but a more Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious ſpectacle, there to be gazed upon by theſe bodily eyes, whereas we are never at a diſtance from him, but only in the diſperſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> multiplicity, diſtraction, and ſcattering of our bo<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>s, and in the diſſimilitude, and diſproportion of our ſoules unto him.</item>
                        <item>III. Another Vulgar and common miſtake is that God doth not require any endeavours or activity of ours in the buſineſſe of Heaven, and that he deales with us in matters of Grace and Glory, as meere ſtocks, and ſtones, and inanimall creatures, and not in any way ſuitable to us as free and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall, for although we cannot make alive the new man in us yet we may concur to the killing, and deſtroying of the old, by refuſing to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the luſts and cravings of it.</item>
                        <item>IIII. Neither are we to entertain this conceit, that God hath found out any other way to ſave his people from Hell and deſtruction, without ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of them from their ſins and wickedneſſes.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Infaelix cujus nulli ſapientia prodeſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb facs="tcp:44697:20"/>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:44697:20"/>
                  <head>What Heaven is, vindicated from the Vulgar mistakes and groſſe conceivings of many.</head>
                  <p>Falſe Goſpellers undermine the true righteouſneſſe of God, and make the Goſpel nothing elſe but a ſlight imagination; we ſhould not entertain any ſuch conceit, as if Chriſt came with any new deviſe to bring men to heaven without the hard labour of mortifying their luſts, as if the intent of his coming was to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgate eaſe and liberty to the fleſh, and by his being crucifyed for us upon the Croſſe, to excuſe our crucifying the old man in our hearts, as if he had found out a way to ſave his people from hell and deſtruction, without ſaving of them from their ſins and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes 1. The poſſibility of attaining that righteouſneſſe that is required of us in the Goſpel it is by the power of Chriſt attainable, or elſe none could enter into the Kingdome of Heaven. He that is born of God ſins not, for his ſeed remaines in him, and he cannot ſin, becauſe he is born of God, and muſt we needs ſay that he that is born of God can and may doe nothing elſe but ſin? is the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall ſeed of Gods holy ſpirit, of Gods eternall word in the hearts of true believers, is nothing elſe but the ſeed of the Serpent, and the Cockatrice Eggs, it is poſſible that the divine nature that the Scripture ſpeaks of, ſhould be nothing elſe but the nature of the Devil, that Gods holy ſpirit in us ſhou<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d make us habitations for it ſelfe to dwell in, and yet ſuffer us at the ſame time to be veſſells of ſin and Satan; is the end of the holy Goſpel not at all to free us from ſin by the power of Chriſt, but only to ſpread a Purple vaile over us, not all to deſtroy the works of the Devill in us, but only to cover them from Gods avenging eye; Is the end of the Goſpel nothing elſe, but to paliate over the diſeaſes of our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, which remain in us ever ſence the fall, and not at all to cure them. If ſo then, ſurely the reaſon of this is either, becauſe Chriſt is not able to overcome ſin and Satan in us, as the <hi>Manikees</hi> of old dreamed, or elſe becauſe he is not willing, and that is a greater diſparagement to him then the former, for the other robbs him only of the Glory of his power, but this ſpoyles him of the Glory of his goodneſs; as if Chriſt ſhould envy that to us, which of all other things is the moſt neceſſary to make us happy; or as if God were not as carefull to advance his Kingdome of light,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:44697:21"/>
here in the world, as the Devill is to inlarge his Kingdome of darkneſſe, as if God did not love his own butifull Image, his own ſon and nature, but would willingly ſuffer it to be choaked and ſmothered here in the world by thoſe Fiends of darkneſſe, whom he hath long ſince lockt and fettered up in chains of darkneſſe, and reſerved for the judgment of the great day. Say's the Philoſopher no man ſets up a marke on purpoſe that men might miſſe it, and ſhall God ſet up this marke of righteouſneſſe in the Goſpel as a Butt for us to aime at, for this very end and purpoſe, that all the world ſhould miſſe it; Can he that is the faithfull and true God put ſuch a trick of fraud and mockery upon his creatures? No ſurely, righteouſneſſe, evangelicall righteouſneſſe is the only thing intended <hi>per,</hi> ſee in all Gods Commandements, and ſin which is nothing elſe but a miſſing of the marke, comes in by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, ſin is that which God will either deſtroy and baniſh out of the World by the clear diſcovery of his truth in the hearts of men, or elſe he will at laſt chain it in the bottomleſſe pit to all eternity, and make the blackneſſe of it to be a ſoyle to ſet off the glory of his juſtice.</p>
                  <p>But it is ſuggeſted by ſome, that Chriſt will not therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow any true righteouſneſſe, holineſſe, or ſanctification upon a Saint, on purpoſe that he might keep him humble, as if the only way to make men truly humble, were to make them wicked, and as it men would be ſo much the more proud, by how much the more holy, and made truly partakers of the image of God. Away then w<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th this fond conceit, whereby we doe nothing elſe but gratifie mens luſts; And ſmother and extinguiſh the life of God in the world, it is the ſluggard that ſayes there is a Lion in the way, but the true beleever ſaith, Who art thou O great moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain before, <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> thou ſhalt become a plain, nay, the truth it ſelfe ſaith, <hi>All things are poſſible to them that beleeve,</hi> we may undoubtedly by the power of God in us, prevaile every day more and more over the power of ſin and Satan, the weapons of our warfare are very powerfull and able to batter down the ſtrong holds of Satan in our hearts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he that is indeed born of God ſhall overcome the world, and the fleſh, and the Devil to, by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God in him, he ſhall deſtroy the law of ſin in his members, by the true Law<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Law of the Spirit of life, and if we ſhould with unfeigned ſimplicity of heart apply our ſelves to God, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:44697:21"/>
reſigning up our ſelvs to him, to be taught &amp; led by him, we ſhould certainly find that his free ſpitit would inwardly lead us into all wayes of obedience, and that it would be as naturall and as delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to us, to walke on in thoſe pleaſant pathes of holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, as ever it was to wander in thoſe crooked wayes of ſin and wickedneſſe; nay the true Regenerate chriſtian, is ſo far from delighting ſecretly in the wayes of ſin, as the falſe hearted hypocrite thinks he doth, that there is nothing that more hurts and wounds his ſoule, then that he hath not a more lively ſence of evill; for the divine life in him being a delicate and tender thing hath the moſt quickeſt ſence of any thing that is contrary to it, and is moſt ingenious and induſtrious for ſelfe preſervation againſt it, wiſdome is eaſie to the wiſe, ſayes <hi>Solomon,</hi> and her wayes are wayes of pleaſantneſſe to them, and all her paths are peace, and ſin is the moſt ugly and forlorn thing in the world Let not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe evill ſpyes that bring an evill report upon this Land of Promiſe, diſhearten and diſcourage us, but let us goe on in the Power of God and his ſtrength, and exerciſe our faith in this, not only that we ſhall be freed from Fire and Brimſtone here after, but that we ſhall be delivered from the power of ſin, and Satan in our own hearts, this is that faith whereby we overcome the world; and if we had more of this faith in the power of Chriſt to deſtroy our corruptions in us, and to tread down Satan under our feete, and all that fond and ungrounded confidence, that God intends to ſave us while we continue under the power of ſin, we ſhould goe on more ſucceſſefully and proſperouſly in the way to Heaven.</p>
                  <p>And it is a dangerous miſtake now under the Goſpel, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that God will ſave men out of a fond affection towards them, without renuing of their natures, and begetting his own ſon the new Creature in their hearts. Meerly for beleeving this very thing, that they ſhall be ſaved, as if it were poſſible for men to be made happy, without being delivered from the power of ſin, which is all one, as if we ſhould ſay that it were poſſible for men to be ſaved without ſalvation, ſurely ſuch as theſe think heaven no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a meer place without them, a fine gliſtering place, whoſe gates are of pearl, and the walls of Jaſper, and the bottome paved with ſtarrs, a very Turkiſh Paradiſe, for had they once taſted of the true pleaſures of the ſoule purg'd from ſin, and really eſtabliſht in the life of God, they would then ſee ſo much defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:44697:22"/>
in ſin, that they would not accept of heaven upon ſuch terms as thoſe that is to be placed in an outward heaven, without the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward change and renuing of their mindes, without the conforming of their ſoules to the Image and likeneſſe of God; I am ſure a true Saint would not take heaven on ſuch conditions as theſe are, that he might enjoy all the outward pleaſures that are poſſible, that he might have a ſhining gliſtering body, that he might tread upon Stars, and flye upon the wings of the winde, that he might converſe with Cherubims and Serafims, Angels and arke Angels, if all this while he muſt continue filthy within, full of noyſome and ſtincking luſts, voyd of divine wiſdome that purges and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the ſoule, having a darke and ſottiſh minde, unruly affection, continually ſtrugling and quarrelling within.</p>
                  <p>God he may indeed diſpence with the puniſhment that belongs to ſin, he may forgive and pardon in reſpect of puniſhment, but he can never account thoſe truly holy, that are truly wicked, and bond ſlaves to ſin and Satan. Now this can never make us happy to be freed only from the puniſhment of ſin; we can never be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, till we be made pertakers of the life of God himſelfe, till we have the ſame minde and life in us that is in God himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>If God ſhould account us righteous, except we were truly poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of a righteouſneſſe within us, I may ſpeak it with reverence, this could doe us no good, no true chriſtian would be contented with it, no more then a man that is ſick, could be contented to be accounted whole, or one that is poor and naked, could be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be accounted rich and cloathed, no more then one that is frozen in a cold winter night, could be contented to be accounted hot, nothing without us can make us really happy, till we be inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made pertakers of the Image of God.</p>
                  <p>But it is very plain and eaſie to diſcover the ground of theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes, becauſe carnal men deſire not ſo much to enjoy heaven, as to be freed from hell, or if they deſire heaven they deſire nothing at all in it, but only their own eaſe and carnall pleaſure, it would ſerve their turn well enough, if they could but have an artifice to get their ſins pardoned, that they might be freed from the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that is due to them, and might be admitted into a ſenſuall heaven, though they live to all eternity under the power of ſin and wickedneſſe, and never have the leſt taſt of the true heavenly Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, nor any knowledge of the name written on the white ſtone,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:44697:22"/>
which no man knowes but he that hath it, and therefore it will ſerve theſe mens turnes well enough, if they may be freed from the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of ſin, while they love ſin with all their hearts, The true hearted chriſtian is really departed out of wicked <hi>Sodom,</hi> out of this noyſome ſtate of ſin, he is not ſo much ſolicitus about his ſtate, as about his life, that he may ſtill continue that heavenly life that is begun in him, he is not ſo anxious about his juſtification in a propoſterous method, as about the ſanctification of his heart and affection; that is the beſt way to be aſſured of his juſtification, he feeles the divine life in him, and that he knowes can never ſink him to hell, he drinkes of the true ſprings of everlaſting life, and knowes he ſhall never ſee death, he is not ſo much perplext about his future ſalvation, becauſe he findes he is already ſaved, becauſe it ſelfe hath taken him upon its wings, and carries him away ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly far from the region of death and Hell. I beſeech you let us not deceive our ſelves, without ſuch an inward frame of ſpirit as this is, that is really crucifyed to the world, and planted into Chriſt, ſucking life and influence from him. God himſelfe with what he can do without us, would never make us happy.</p>
                  <p>Beſides the deſtroying of this corrupt, naturall, and fleſhly life, we muſt alſo have a new and ſpirituall life begotten in us; For as Chriſt and the divine nature did aſſume the humane nature to it ſelfe, ſo likewiſe in every chriſtian the divine life, or the life of God muſt as it were aſſume the humane and created life of man, and totally act it and inforce it, this is the eſſence of the new creature, this is the life and ſoul of chriſtianity, the marrow and quinteſſence of all religion, to have a life wrapped up in man, that is the very life of God himſelfe, and whoſoever doth not pertake of this life, whatſoever opinion he entertains in religion, whatever outward forms of diſcipline he contends for, whatever ſects he belongs to, he is either carnall or deviliſh. For nothing of mans is pleaſing unto God, but that that God workes in man, and by man, and whatſoever workes with God according to that that is in God, this is in a manner one ſpirit with God himſelfe, and whatſoever it doth, it doth it in <hi>Forma Dei,</hi> that is, God uſing this mans ſoule and life, and abilities, doth act it in him. But whatſoever perticular created life, lives otherwiſe then the eternall life of God lives, this ſets up it ſelfe againſt God, and this is the life of corrupt nature, and the life of the Devill, this is ſin and nothing elſe, to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:44697:23"/>
live otherwiſe then the eternal life of God lives, and this was that that Chriſt came into the world to deſtroy, and how doth he doe this? ſurely no otherwiſe then by bringing Gods own life into the humanity; Again, for he himſelfe was nothing elſe but a Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of God pitched amongſt men, nothing but a humane nature acted, and diſpoſed, and guided by the life of God, ſo that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Chriſt lives, God lives in him, now this muſt not only be done by Chriſt without us, but the ſame alſo muſt be done within us.</p>
                  <p>One groſſe miſtake among men, that yet pretend much to Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that is very prejudiciall to the advancement of this ſpirituall righteouſneſſe that the Goſpel requires of us, and that is a conſeite that men have whereby they think that ſalvation is a meer outward work, and therefore may be wholly effected by outward means, whereas it is nothing elſe for the ſubſtance of it, but the inward transforming of our ſelves into the likeneſſe of God, the reall tranſlating of us out of the life of nature, into the divine life, or life of God, or the begetting of a new and heavenly life in the ſoule of man, that is the very ſame that doth every way agree with the life of God himſelfe; I ſay it with reverence God himſelfe cannot make us happy by any thing without us, but only by form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own nature and likeneſſe in us, they are carnall and earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly minded men, and no way ſuitable to the ſtate of glory and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, that fancy the happineſſe of heaven to conſiſt only in things without them, and look upon it only as an outward place, and not as an inward ſtate and diſpoſition of the ſoule; I ſay there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that ſalvation it is an inward thing, and conſiſts chiefly in being ſaved from our ſins, and being delivered from our own life, and being tranſlated out of the Kingdome of darkneſſe into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of light and righteouſneſſe, and it is not a Heaven without us, though never ſo glorious and gliſtering a place, nay, it is not God without us that can make us truly and really happy, but it is God inwardly, ſetting himſelfe in our ſoules, and ſo dwelling in us that our ſins may be ſo ruled and guided by the life of God, as the members of our bodies are acted by our ſoules, and when this is once done, we ſhall at once live both the life of God, and injoy the joy, peace, and happineſſe of God himſelfe, which will all at once flow in upon us, I would not be miſtaken, I doe not here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but that there be ſome other inferiour circumſtances belonging
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:44697:23"/>
to the ſtate of happineſſe, as the changing of theſe vild bodies of ours, and inſtead of this earthly tabernacle that weighs down the minde, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeakes, when as our ſoules were as it were now buried in a heepe of fleſh, they ſhall receive an other more divine Tabernacle that <hi>Paul</hi> calls a ſpirituall body, a more fit com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion for our ſoules, and many other ſuch things anſwerable here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, I ſay theſe things I doe not deny, but yet all theſe things are of an inferiour nature, and all depend upon the former, the inward frame and diſpoſition of the ſoule, in which the ſubſtance of heaven and hell conſiſt. Now this being well conſider'd and underſtood, it is very plain that to thinke we can be ſaved without inward righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, meerly by ſomething done without us, without the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and reall change of our ſoules; is all one as to thinke we can be ſaved without ſalvation, or we can be made happy without the poſſeſſion of happineſſe, though we muſt ſtill remember the only procuring cauſe of our ſalvation, is the death ſufferings and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of Chriſt, who was made a propitiation for our ſins, this is therefore the reaſon for which this inward righteouſneſſe before ſpoken of is to be urged in the Goſpel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not as if we could thereby merrit any thing at all at the hands of God, for we can merrit no thing, but there is nothing that God himſelfe can beſtow upon us in heaven better, then the partiſipation of his own life and nature, this inward change of the ſoul, this new creature is ſalvation it ſelf, and if we be not poſſeſſed of it in ſome meaſure here, we have little reaſon how ever we may fondly flatter our ſelves to think it ſhall be done hereafter, that is the firſt miſtake that I ſhall take notice of, that we are apt to conceive that ſalvation is an outward worke, and may be wrought only by outward means.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. There is another miſtake that is very neer a kin to that in matters of religion, and that is, when we ſeek for God we looke for God wholly abroad without our ſelves, whereas the only way to finde God is to turn our ſelves inward, and to looke for him in the bottome of our own ſoules, for if we could be carried up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ſpheares, and pry into every corner of the ſtarrs in heaven above, certainly we ſhould as little find God there as we did on earth, if we could find God any where abroad without us, this could not make us happy, for then God would be really at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from us, but our happineſſe conſiſts in ſuch a reall commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God, as our Saviour diſcribes, 17 <hi>Joh.</hi> 22. <hi>The glory
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:44697:24"/>
which thou gaveſt me, I have given them, that they may be one as we are one; I in them, and they in me, that all might be made perfect in one</hi>: The heaven where God dwells in, and where alone he is to be found, is in a regenerate ſoul, and he that will indeed find God and be united to him, muſt not gaze and gad abroad, and turn his eyes wholly outward, but he muſt look to find him within, <hi>Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis animis,</hi> for there he may at once both ſee him, feele him, taſte him, and be united to him, God is never diſtant by place from us, for in him we live and move and have our being, but all our diſtance from him is only in the diſperſion, multiplicity, deſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſcatterings of our hearts, and in the diſſimilitude and diſproportions of our ſoules unto him, and when theſe things are once removed, then God appears to us who was never abſent from us, but only our eyes are now unvailed to ſee and behold him, God is every where alike to him that can feele him, he is only not preſent to him that cannot receive him, as the ſun ſhines not in a houſe where the curtains are drawn, and the windowes ſtopt up. This is the reaſon why many have ſo much adoe to finde God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they look for him as a corporall thing, they ſtill imploy their fanſies and imaginations to finde him without, and ſend them a roving, gadding, and wandering abroad after God, and have ſuch naturall and groſſe conceits of heaven, as if it were nothing but a Theatre, a place of ſights and ſhows, and God himſelfe were nothing but a more pompeous ſpectacle, there to be gazed upon by theſe bodily eyes; God I ſay is to be ſought by a Chriſtian within his own ſoule, and the way to find him there is, not by knowledge; or ſtudy, or ſpeculation, but by a leaving off all things, even our own wit and knowledge, and eſpecially our lives, and by abſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our ſelves from the love of the world, and of our ſelves, and dying to them, and then out of this death will ſpring the true and heavenly light in which alone God is ſeen and known.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. There is yet another miſtake that is very vulgar and common, and that is, that men are generally very apt to conceive that God doth not require any endeavours, any activity of ours at all in the buſineſſe of Religion, and that God deales with us in matters of grace and ſpirituall things, as meer ſtockes, and ſtones, and inani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal creatures, and not in a way ſuitable to us, as we are free and rationall; This I conceive to be another miſtake that damps and choakes mens endeavours of ſubduing and mortifying their luſts,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:44697:24"/>
for by this means we lazily ly down under the burden of our ſins, and think we may caſt the blame of our wickedneſs upon God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, he hath not given us ſtrength, he hath not given us power and ability, this is a ſtrong caſtle of ſin, in which men are apt to gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon themſelves againſt all the hearty exhortations and inſtructions which the Word of God, and the meſſengers of God bring unto them, whereas the Scripture every where calls upon us, to <hi>work out our ſalvation with fear and trembling, to make our calling and electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſure, to gird up the loyns of our minds, to fight the good fight of faith,</hi> and Chriſt himſelfe tells us, <hi>That he with his ſpirit ſtands at the doore and knocks, if any man open, and will hear his voyce, I will come into him,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and ſup with him, and he with me</hi>; It is true, indeed it is not in our power to make our ſelves new creatures, to be regenerate and born again when we pleaſe, but as our Saviour tells us, <hi>the winde blowes where it liſteth, and thou heareſt the ſound thereof, and canst not tell whence it comes, nor whither it goeth, ſo is every one that is born of the Spirit,</hi> but yet let us not deceive our ſelves, though this change in us be a new birth, and we cannot make our ſelves the ſons of God, no more then we can make our ſelves the Sons of men, we can indeed but <hi>Pati Deum,</hi> lye down and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer while he prints his own Image on our hearts, while he forms himſelfe in our ſoules; yet notwithſtanding let us not deceive our ſelves, there is ſomething for us to doe, and that the Scripture e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where calls upon us for, and that is, <hi>not to make proviſion for the fleſh, to fulfill the luſts thereof, to put off the old man that is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, according to the deceitfull luſts, to mortifie and ſubdue this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of death, that we carry about us,</hi> for though we cannot make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live the new man in us when we pleaſe, yet we may concurr to the killing and deſtroying of the old, by refuſing to ſatisfie the luſts &amp; cravings of it, &amp; then by looking up to heaven, &amp; imploring Gods aſſiſtance that he would come down upon us the ſecond time, &amp; breath into us the breath of ſupernaturall life, we have therefore many gracious promiſes made to us in the Goſpel, on purpoſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage us to faith in God, that he will be always ready to prevent us with his goodneſſe, &amp; to remove the wretched infidelity of our hearts, whereby our confidence in God is choaked &amp; all heavenly endeavours are dampt in us, the whole Goſpel was written to this end &amp; purpoſe, to deſtroy this infidelity, and aſſure us that we may come to God, &amp; that he is a rewarder of thoſe that ſeek him.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
